RG 074:003, David N. Gaines Genealogical Papers
Connecticut State Library
David N. Gaines genealogical papers
1891-1940
Connecticut State Library
Gaines, David N., 1854-1941
3 cubic feet
David N. Gaines (1854-1941) served as the town clerk, judge of probate, postmaster, and secretary and treasurer of the First Ecclesiastical Society in Hartland. His genealogical papers consist of notes on old houses, vital statistics, East Hartland Cemetery and various Hartland families.
RG074_003
1941-003
Biographical Note
David Gaines was born in Hartland, Conn. in 1854 and lived there until his death in 1941. Gaines served the community in several capacities: postmaster for the east section (East Hartland) for over thirty-five years; town clerk; judge of probate; secretary and treasurer of the First Ecclesiastical Society for sixty years; and sexton of the East Hartland Cemetery for more that fifty years, being responsible for much of the rebuilding and beautification of the grounds. A lifelong Republican, Gaines served as a representative in the General Assembly in 1899 and in 1921.
While town clerk, Gaines became interested in land records and genealogies of the early settlers of Hartland. He also gathered data on the First Ecclesiastical Society, its earliest ministers and various changes made to the church building. He spent many years researching the connections of Hartland men who served in the Revolutionary War and other wars.
Gaines compiled a map in 1916 of all the homes still standing, as well as abandoned homes. He marked bridle paths and discontinued roads. This map along with the map compiled by Cornell Tiffany of West Hartland helped explain the land divisions and lots drawn up in the early 1700s and given to the early proprietors
Known as the "Sage of East Hartland", Gaines was considered a living legend in the town. A recording of his voice has been preserved as an outstanding example of typical New England speech.
Sources
Bartlett, Sally. "Residents Can Consult 'Gaines Notes'." Hartford Courant, 1976 August 27, 27C.
"David Gaines 'Seer,' Dies in Hartland." Hartford Courant, 1941 September 27, 4.
"History and Map of Hartland Homes." Hartford Courant, 1917 February 13, 5.
"The Sage of East Hartland." Hartford Courant, 1941 September 28, A2.
"Sage of East Hartland." Hartford Courant, 1940 January 28, SM3.
"The Sage of East Mountain." Hartford Courant, 1932 January 31, E3.
Scope and Content
The bulk of the papers consist of photostatic copies of Gaines' notebooks. The house survey notes trace the ownership of Hartland area homes from 1749 to 1916. The container list indicates the names identified in the key to each "set" as provided by Gaines. Vital statistics notes include information on births, marriages and deaths in Hartland. Other notes cover the East Hartland Cemetery and a number of Hartland families. Also present is one of Gaines' original notebooks containing news clippings and vital statistics, along with a photostatic copy. Finally, name and address cards are arranged by town. Respondents were asked to indicated if they had any Hartland ancestors.
Arrangement
Arranged into eight series as follows: House survey notes, Vital statistics notes, East Hartland Cemetery notes, Notes on families, Notebook, News clippings, Miscellaneous, and Name and address cards. The majority of the notes are arranged by set: A-Z, AA-ZZ, AAA-DDD, followed by unlettered sets.
Related Material
Gaines, David N., compiler. Birth, marriage, death records, 1850-1933, taken from Hartland town records; Cemetery records from East Hartland Cemetery, 1770-1933; Genealogical notes of Bushnell, Gaines & Tillotson Families, 1617-1927 [CSL call number StLib Archives 920 G12].
Gaines, David N., compiler. Hartland church records. Photostat of manuscript copy [CSL call number StLib Archives 974.62 fH261c J].
Gaines, David N., compiler. Key to East Hartland homesteads [CSL call number StLib Archives 974.62 J26:Eg K].
Gaines, David N., compiler. Key numbers to old house places in East Hartland [as per map drawn by C.H. Tiffany and D.N. Gaines] [CSL call number StLib Archives 974.62 H26:Eg KE].
Gaines, David H. and Correl H. Tiffany. Map of Hartland, both East Hartland and West Hartland, showing location of homesteads, mills, highways, etc. from earliest times to 1911. Photostat of original loaned by David N. Gaines [CSL call number StLib Archives 912.7462 H26t map case].
Record made by David N. Gaines to record his voice [CSL Call Number StLib Archives 920 G12].
Tiffany, Correll H., compiler. Key to West Hartland Homesteads [CSL call number 974.62 fH26:Wti K].
Tiffany, Correll H., compiler. West Hartland Homesteads, circa 1913-1914 [CSL call number 974.62 H26:Wti d].
Index Terms
Persons:
Gaines, David N., 1854-1941
Places:
Hartland (Conn.) -- Genealogy; Connecticut -- Genealogy
Subjects:
Historic buildings -- Connecticut -- Hartland
Document Types:
News clippings; Notebooks; Postal cards
Restrictions on Access
These records are stored at an off-site facility and therefore may not be available on a same-day basis.
See the policy.
Provenance
David Gaines' diary along with Barkhamsted Church record were received from David N. Gaines on May 14, 1941.
Container List
- Series 1. House survey notes, circa 1910-1916; negative photostat
  - Set A (Box 1, Folder 1)
    1. Jonathan Bogue; 2. Abram Osborn; 21. Daniel Frazier; 25. John Andrus (Andrew); 24. Nehemiah Andrus (Andrew); 241. Abram Osborn cider mill; 23. Hezekiah Ackly; 22. Jonathan Couch.
  - Set B (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Hartland Green 1. Joel Meacham, Henry Gates; Hartland Green 3. John Gates; Hartland Green 4. Burying ground; 73. First school house, stone school house; Hartland Green 5. William Chapman, Lewis Emmons, William L. Hayes; 128. Solomon Toby.
  - Set C (Box 1, Folder 2)
    3. Miron Miller, Thomas Beeman; 3a. Thomas Beeman potash works; 4. Reuben Beeman; 7. Reuben Miller; 7a. Daniel Rathborn, Attenbury Smith blacksmith shop; 241. Abram Osborn cider mill distillery; 6. Stone school house.
  - Set D (Box 1, Folder 2)
    All Hartland Green: 9. Parsonage, Nelson Scott; 10. Dr. Homer G. Bell; 11. Watson Gibbons; 14. Jared Newel, Benjamin Gidding; 13. Hotel now owned by George W. Carr, E.C. Emmons; 14a. Cooper shop; 15. Mary A. Hurlburt cottage.
  - Set E (Box 1, Folder 3)
    11. Willis Wright; 10. Solomon E. Miller; 12. Silas Giddings; 9. Harry Miller; 8. Peter Holcomb; 14. John Atwood; 13. Ezra Miller; 15. Caleb Moses, House place on east side of road; 237. Private cemetery; 201. Ichabod Fuller; 214. Moosehorn Brook, 251. Willis Wright distillery, 80. Peter Holcomb old house, 252. Edwin Frazier cider mill, 10a. Stanley K. Dimock.
  - Set F (Box 1, Folder 3)
    East Hartland Green 12. Meeting House; East Hartland Green 6. Uriel Holimes; East Hartland Green 7. Milo J. Giddings, David N. Gaines; East Hartland Green 8. M.E. Church; 9a. Eli Andrus (Andrew); X. Mrs. Leslie Dutton - F.C. Gould; Y. Flossie Vibbits; Z. F.C. Gould.
  - Set G (Box 1, Folder 4)
    19. Orson Gates, Lester Cowdry (Cowdery); 17. Amos Seward; 16. Samuel Skinner; 5. Daniel Beman; 18. E.H. Miller; 16a. Cider mill; 15. Caleb Moses; 16. Unwin Gates; 15a. Martin Moses.
  - Set H (Box 1, Folder 4)
    20. John Sweet; 26. Absalom Graham; 27. Deacon Thomas Giddings; 28. Aaron Cowles; 205. First saw mill Thomas Gidding; Hartland Green 16. William Smilly; Hartland Green 17. Harold Smith; Hartland Green 18. P. Kingsbury; 189. Jonathan Shipman; 19. Brewster Highway; 224. U. Holmes or T. Gidding saw mill; 205. U. Holmes or T. Gidding dam; 116. S. Beech, E. Palmer, U. Holmes.
  - Set I (Box 1, Folder 5)
    29. Joseph Foote; 30-31. John Borden; 47. Jeffery O. Phelps; 45. Roswell Elmore; 46. Eliphalet Parker; 247. Charles Wright; 247a. Benjamin Parker; 45b. Ben Hoadley.
  - Set J (Box 1, Folder 5)
    32. Benjamin Place; 248. East of Benjamin Place; No key west of Benjamin Place 45a; 33. Levi P. Case; 34. Henry Carmer; 35. A.B. Gaines spring house; No key number east of no. 33-34 in pasture; 2-- [not legible]. L.P. Case steam mill; 43. The old Jaris Case house; William Chapman no key no. 33a; Benjamin Parker no 247a; 75a. Joel Minor south of Enos Lane blacksmith shop; 43a. Hiram Bushman; 202. Tolson House; 248. Elisha Cowles; 45a. Joel Minor west of Benjamin Place)); 44. Strong Sanford.
  - Set K (Box 1, Folder 6)
    48. Thomas Fuller, George D. Cornish; 49. John Giddings; 50. Edward Brockway; No key number 50a. Moses Brockway; No 48a. Joshua Giddings; XBD. bear den; 50a. Moses Brockway; 50b. Edward Brockway Jr.; Vol. 3-352. Survey of road north of Brockway.
  - Set L (Box 1, Folder 6)
    52. Enos Lane Jr.; 53. Charles Kellogg; 54. West wood schoolhouse; 55. Jonathan Rathborn; 188. Adna Gillett; 56. Jonathan Herrick; 56a. Obediah Gildersleve, the survey of Brockway road; 57. Phineas Meacham; 55a. Old Taylor house; 51a. Moses Holcomb; A. old house place in Chase lot; B. Chase summer cottage.
  - Set M (Box 1, Folder 7)
    58. Dr. Emmons pest house; 59. Reuben B. Mowrey; 60. Samuel Banning; 61A, 61. Asahel Brainard; 64. William Selby; 63. Simeon Baxter; No key no. northeast 63a. Joseph and Mary Church; 60a. Charles Coombs; 61b. Porter.
  - Set N (Box 1, Folder 7)
    67. Alexander Bushnell; 263. Jonathan Bill, S.G. Bushnell; 140. Elihu Remmington; 139. David Banning; 265. Thomas Bushnell; 264. Charles Coe distillery; 141. Phineas Coe; 167a. Coplin Lake; 220. Bush Brook, Ichabod Grimes; 262. Samuel Banning.
  - Set O (Box 1, Folder 8)
    68, 70. Samuel Skinner; 62. Asa Haines, also blacksmith shop; 69. Brewer and Clement; 71. Rev. Starling Graves; 72. Town pound; 73. First schoolhouse; 65. Aaron Bush; 66. Charles Phelps; 133. Eperiam French; 245. B. Gidding sheep barn; Hartland Green 128. S. Toby, H.E. Bowers; 245a. Attenbury Smith blacksmith shop; 68a. William W. Clark barn.
  - Set P (Box 1, Folder 8)
    74. Asa Andrus, Joshua Giddings; 75. Phineas Perkins, Enos Lane, Myron Searles; 76. Benjamin Hutchens; 79. Rev. Aaron Church; 77. William Bowers; 75a. Joel Minor blacksmith shop; 78. Schoolhouse; X. Dutton cottage; Y. Vibbits cottage; Z. Gould cottage; 46 AB.
  - Set Q (Box 1, Folder 9)
    81. Dr. Philander Humphrey; 80. Horace Emmons; 233. Humphrey store; 18a. A. Church.
  - Set R (Box 1, Folder 9)
    89. Isaac Meacham; 88. Isaac Meacham log house; 84. Gideon Perkins; 85. Uriah Church; 88. Joseph Taylor, Isaac Meacham; 84a. Ranno Cossett; 82. Amos Perkins; 85a. Micah Scovell; 186. Timothy Brockway; 186. southwest of Welsh place on top of hill; 82a. Fred Crane; 88a. Roger Wadworth; B. Clemans mill; 84a. north side of Welsh lot; 84b. Waters house east of Welsh; 82. Phineas Perkins, Abel Moses.
  - Set S (Box 1, Folder 10)
    91. Jonathan Shipman, David Shipman; 90. Stephan Hosmer; 93. Benjamin Reed, William Roberts; 92. Pelatiah Daniels Jr.; 92a. Stephan Hosmer; 93a. Ambrose Cowdry Jr.; 93B. Timothy Gibbons, Asa Cowdry; 94. Hiram Gibbons; 95. William Seymour.
  - Set T (Box 1, Folder 10)
    102. Thomas Wadworth lot no. 26-221a; 102 Jaben Clark; 107. John Jones; 195. Charles Jones log house; 98-99. William Phillips, Benjamin Meacham; 256. Timothy Gibbons; 97. Micah Scovell; 100. Abijah Buttles; 216. Tom Gillett; 196. Dr. John Jones.
  - Set U (Box 1, Folder 11)
    11a. Lewis Emmons; 111. John Daniels; 96. Amherst Daniels; 112. Jaben Clark, Elmar Clark; 117. Ambrose Cowdry; 124. Jesse Gates, Benajah Bill; 127. Theophilus Gates; 126=125. Clay pits; 125a. schoolhouse; 125. Nathan Gates; 196. Dr. John Jones; 256. Timothy Gibbons; 116. Lester Jones distillery; 92a. Stephen Hosmer; 97a. Aaron Warner.
  - Set V (Box 1, Folder 11)
    122. John Church 2nd; 122a. Jesse Gates; 86. Margret Card; 87. Uriah Church; 115. Alman Cowdry; 114. John F. Cowdry, Simeon Clark; 109. Reuben Daniels; 109a. Daniel Jones; 113. Schoolhouse; 110. Roderick Jones; 86a. Card's dam; 106. Hiram Jones; 216. Thomas Gillett.
  - Set W (Box 1, Folder 12)
    123. Calvin Fuller, Silas Holcomb; 123a. Reubin Daniels; 122. John Church 2nd; 121. Moses Cowdry Jr.; 118. Asa Cowdry; 116. Abijah Church; 120. Moses Cowdry Sr.; 119. James N. Cowdry.
  - Set X (Box 1, Folder 12)
    132. Willis Clemans; 130. 3rd schoolhouse; 131. 2nd schoolhouse; 129. Eperiam Selby, O.C. Gates; 134. Aaron Gates; 191. Ira Goodsell; 136. Abner Banning distillery; 131a. Ebenezer Belden; 244. Town pound, O.C. Gates; 132. Asher French monument hill; 192. Asa Scranton.
  - Set Y (Box 2, Folder 1)
    135. Abner Banning; 137. Daniel Bushnell; 142. Samuel Banning, J.D. Emmons; 146. Jonathan Bill; 147/147a. Jonathan Bill Jr., Daniel Bill; 143. Hutchens lot; 140a. William Bushnell; 139a. Daniel Bill; 149a. Jonathan Bill Jr.
  - Set Z (Box 2, Folder 1)
    144. Adna Gillett; 145. Warren Emmons; 145a. Eperiam Wright; 150. Old house foot of Enoch hill; 165a. Alfred Cables; 165b. Samuel Miller; 166. Giles Lawton; 166a. Elijah Clark; 166b. Cobbs sawmill; 240a. Judson Spelman; A. Benoni Evins; 219ab. Spencer Loomis.
  - Set AA (Box 2, Folder 2)
    165. Sawyer; 164a. John Hayes; 164. Judah Twining; 156. Titus Hayes; 157. Reuben Burnham; 200. Schoolhouse; 200a. Old schoolhouse; 26. Sawmill; C. Creamery; 219. Stephen Hibbard.
  - Set BB (Box 2, Folder 2)
    168. Cornwall Clark, T.T. Banning; 168a. Jonathan Couch; 169. Holcomb; 170. Richardson; 171. Asariah Stebbins; 219. David Couch, Phineas Perkins.
  - Set CC (Box 2, Folder 3)
    172. Homer Fuller; No key no. John Kendall; 223. Capt. Oliver Bates; Charles Trankett; 182. Seth Roberts; 235. Hartland cemetery.
  - Set DD (Box 2, Folder 3)
    174. Virgil Stebbins; 175. Town house; 176. Asa Smith; 177. Nathan Hatch; 59. Reuben Mowrey; 177a. Daniel Ensign; 259. Toll gate.
  - Set EE (Box 2, Folder 4)
    219. Abner Bushnell.
  - Set FF (Box 2, Folder 4)
    266. Holmes mill; 159. Richard Hayes = Luther Burham; 159a. Samuel Benjamin; 152. Elijah Clark = vis Coe; 158a. A. Smith cloth mill; A. Ely Andrus house; 1a. Edward Smith blacksmith shop; 2a. Burham distillery.
  - Set GG, Key numbers sent to State Library care of George S. Goddard; Key numbers to East Hartland part of map. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Set HH, Survey of the division (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Set II, Survey by Bethuel Beman (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Set JJ, Untitled surveying notes (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - West Hartland houses compiled by Correll H. Tiffany, circa 1911 (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - Duplicates (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series 2. Vital statistics notes, circa 1910-1915; negative photostat
  - Set KK, Vol. 1, Births-marriages-deaths from 1784-1867 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Set LL, Vol. 2, Records of births in town of Hartland from 1852-1869 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Set MM, Vol. 2, Deaths in town of Hartland from 1852-1869 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Set NN, Vol. 2, Marriages in town of Hartland from 1852-1869, and to 1916 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Set OO, Births from 1869 in town of Hartland (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Set PP, Vol. 3, Records of deaths in Hartland from 1869-1915 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Set QQ, Marriages in town of Hartland from 1869-1915 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Set RR, Births-marriages-deaths, 1888-1899 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Set SS, Deaths commencing January 1917 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Set TT, Deaths and burials in Hartland from 1918 to (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Series 3. East Hartland Cemetery notes, 1921; negative photostat
  - Set UU, East of gate, 1920 May 10; O.P. Cowdery (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Set VV, West of gate, 1920 May 11; O.P. Cowdery (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Series 4. Notes on families, circa 1910-1920; negative photostat
  - Set WW, Nehemiah Andrus (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Set XX, Capt. Alexander Bushnell family (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Set YY, George Coltan (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Set ZZ, Giddings family, what part is connected to Hartland Conn from 1754 to 1900 by Minot S. Giddins (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Set AAA, McCloud; Roger Veites record; Osborn; Bogue; Frazier; Miner; Rowe (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Set BBB, Joel Tiffany and Hannah Wilder; Rufus French; Daniel Huxford; Benjamin H. Banning children-g-children copy from family bible, 1920 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Set CCC, Wilder families (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Set DDD, Untitled (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Duplicates of lettered sets (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Richard Hayes, Micah Scovell, William Roberts, Benjamin Reed; Coult family, Eli Strong, David Gidding, Capt. Jaben Clark, Rev. Aaron Church, Rowland Stebbins; Lieut. John Andrews (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Bushnell; Samuel Banning, Phineas Coe; Dr. Dennis, James Carnick (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Edwin P. Jones family, Obed Crosby; Northway and Gaines; Granville Mass. earlier settlers (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Jonathan Shipman, Hezekiah Ackley, Strong, David Kellogg; Votes from Hartland town book; Johnson, Pyam Baillett, John Coreys, Aaron Cook (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - William Cowdery, Henry A. Brown; Loomis, Mead, Seward, Gates, Samuel Twining; Review of Beman - Ackley evidence (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Grand Jury complaints and court Hartland, Dr. O.W. Kellogg, Joseph Carrier, Dr. Jeremiah Emmons, Hezekiah Ackley; Parts of letters received from different persons, T.A. Bushnell, Ruben Hale, Joseph Dewolf, Peter Gibbons, Horace Roberts, Daniel King; William Beman, Stephen Gates, William Shipman, William Baillett (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Genealogy and biography of the first settlers of Hartford; Divisions of the town of Hartford about 1640, no. 2 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Genealogy and biography of the first settlers of Harford, no. 3; Genealogy and biography of the first settlers of Harford, no. 4 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Dr. Jeremiah Emmons children, Thomas Burham, Litchfield county Emmons, Beman Gates, Thomas Emmons; Granville, Samuel Blakeslee (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous and duplicates (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Series 5. Notebook, circa 1891-1917
  - Notebook with news clippings and vital statistics (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Copy of notebook, negative photostat (Box 4, Folder 6-10)
- Series 6. News clippings, 1925-1939
  - News clippings (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Series 7. Miscellaneous, 1906, 1937-1940, undated
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5, Folder 12)
    Includes the East Hartland Cemetery Association, Inc. treasurer's report, 1938.
- Series 8. Name and address cards, undated
  - Name and address cards (Box 6)
    Arranged by alphabetically by town. States other than Connecticut are at the end.
    Question on cards ask if the respondent has any Hartland ancestors.